<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document><head><organization>ISO/IEC</organization><document-type>International Standard</document-type><stage>enquiry</stage><tc-number>1</tc-number><tc-name>Information Technology</tc-name><sc-number>34</sc-number><sc-name>Document Description and Processing Languages</sc-name><wg-number>1</wg-number><serial-number>0</serial-number><document-number>19757</document-number><part-number>11</part-number><document-language>E</document-language><secretariat>IPSJ/ITSCJ</secretariat><date>2010-09-10</date><title><introductory>Information Technology</introductory><main>Document Schema Definition Languages (DSDL)</main><complementary>Schema Association</complementary></title><editor>Jirka Kosek</editor></head><foreword><p><This/> is being jointly developed by W3C and ISO/IEC JTC1/SC34. 
        The technical content of this specification and that of <xref to="xml-model"/> is expected to be identical.</p><part-list><part><number>1</number><title>Overview</title></part><part><number>2</number><title>Grammar-based validation — RELAX NG</title></part><part><number>3</number><title>Rule-based validation — Schematron</title></part><part><number>4</number><title>Namespace-based validation dispatching language — NVDL</title></part><part><number>5</number><title>Extensible Datatypes</title></part><part><number>6</number><title>Path-based integrity constraints</title></part><part><number>7</number><title>Character repertoire description language — CREPDL</title></part><part><number>8</number><title>Document schema renaming language — DSRL</title></part><part><number>9</number><title>Datatype- and namespace-aware DTDs</title></part><part><number>10</number><title>Validation management</title></part><part><number>11</number><title>Schema Association</title></part></part-list></foreword>Associating Schemas with XML documents1.0 (First Edition)NOTE-xml-model-20100415W3C Working Group Note15April2010 http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/NOTE-xml-model-20100415/ XMLhttp://www.w3.org/TR/xml-model/<introduction><p><em>(This section is non-normative.)</em></p><p>There are several document schema definition languages in common

use today that can be used to specify one or more validation processes

performed against Extensible Markup Language (XML) documents. Some

schema languages provide their own syntax for associating schemas

with documents (DTD, W3C XML Schema) and some languages (RELAX NG,

Schematron) do not provide schema association mechanisms at all. The

purpose of this specification is to define a common, schema-agnostic

syntax for associating schema documents written in any schema definition

language with a given XML document.</p><p>This specification defines the syntax and processing expectations

for an xml-model processing instruction. Such processing instructions

associate one or more schemas with the XML document in which they

are present. The associated schemas may be written in any schema definition

language. Applications can use the associated schemas for any purpose

including those such as document validation, content completion in

interactive editors, or creating models for data binding. Presence

of an xml-model processing instruction is not in itself an instruction

to any processor to validate the document, nor is it a statement that

the document is not to be processed without validation. It is a declarative

statement of a relationship between the document and one or more external

schemas.</p><p>It should be noted that this specification is not meant as a replacement

for other technologies that provide more general and indirect schema

association features like NVDL and XProc. This specification is complementary

technology which can be used when it is necessary to store ad-hoc

schema associations directly inside XML document.</p></introduction><scope><p>This document allows schemas using any schema definition language

to be associated with an XML document by including one or more processing

instructions with a target of <code>xml-model</code> in the document's

prolog.</p></scope><normative-references><referenced-document id="assocss"><abbrev>ASSOCSS</abbrev><title><field>Associating

Style Sheets with XML documents 1.0 (Second Edition)</field></title><field>. W3C, 4 December 2009.</field><url>http://www.w3.org/XML/2009/12/xml-stylesheet/</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="ianacharset"><abbrev>IANACHARSET</abbrev><title><field>Character Sets</field></title><field>. IANA, May 2007.</field><url>http://www.iana.org/assignments/character-sets</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="infoset"><abbrev>INFOSET</abbrev><title><field>XML Information Set</field></title><field>, J. Cowan, R. Tobin. W3C,

February 2004.</field><url>http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="iso-iec_19757-3_6.1"><abbrev>ISO/IEC 19757-3</abbrev><title><field>ISO/IEC

19757-3:2006. Information technology — Document Schema Definition

Languages (DSDL) — Part 3: Rule-based validation — Schematron</field></title><field>, International Organization for Standardization and International

Electrotechnical Commission. 2006.</field></referenced-document><referenced-document id="rfc2119"><abbrev>RFC2119</abbrev><title><field>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement

Levels</field></title><field>, S. Bradner. IETF, March 1997.</field><url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="rfc3987"><abbrev>RFC3987</abbrev><title><field>Internationalized Resource Identifiers (IRIs)</field></title><field>, M. Dürst, M. Suignard. IETF, January 2005.</field><url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3987.txt</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="xml"><abbrev>XML</abbrev><title><field>Extensible Markup Language</field></title><field>, T. Bray, J. Paoli, C. Sperberg-McQueen,

E. Maler, F. Yergeau. W3C, November 2008.</field><url>http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</url></referenced-document><referenced-document id="xml-model"><abbrev>XML-MODEL</abbrev><title>Associating Schemas with XML documents 1.0 (First Edition), </title><field>P. Grosso, </field><field>J. Kosek. </field><field>W3C, April 2010.</field><url>http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-model/</url></referenced-document></normative-references><clause><title> Conformance requirements</title><p>All diagrams, examples, and notes in this specification are non-normative,

as are all sections explicitly marked non-normative. Everything else

in this specification is normative.</p><constraint><title>Documents</title><p>A document is considered to conform to this specification if it

satisfies all  criteria in this specification

that apply to documents.</p></constraint><constraint><title>xml-model processors</title><p>XML defines an <i>application</i> as a software module which receives the information content of an

XML document from an <i>XML processor</i>. <termdef>An <term>xml-model processor</term> is such an application which

processes XML <i>processing instructions</i> in accordance with this specification.</termdef> </p><p>An xml-model processor may be part of a larger XML application, or may function independently. In either case, <termdef>an <term>application</term> is the consumer of the pseudo-attribute information defined in this

specification.</termdef></p><p>An xml-model processor is considered to be a conforming xml-model processor if it satisfies all  criteria in this specification that apply to xml-model processors; xml-model processors do not

have to check or enforce any of the constraints on documents.</p></constraint><p>This specification is defined with reference to the vocabulary

for XML provided by the XML Information Set as well as the <i>rules for parsing pseudo-attributes

from a string</i> as defined in the Associating Style Sheets

with XML documents Recommendation <xref to="assocss"/>.</p><p>The productions in this specification use the same notation as

used in the XML Recommendation. Tokens in the grammar and terms used

in this specification that are not defined in this specification are

defined in the XML Recommendation <xref to="xml"/> or the Associating

Style Sheets <xref to="assocss"/> Recommendation.</p></clause><clause><title>The xml-model processing instruction</title><p><termdef>A processing instruction

information item is said to be a <term>potential xml-model processing

instruction</term> if it has the [target] property <code>xml-model</code> and it is in the [children] property of a document information item

and appears before the element information item of the document information

item's [children] property.</termdef></p><p>For such potential xml-model

processing instructions, xml-model processors shall report to

the application the <i>parsing result</i> of

invoking the <i>rules for parsing

pseudo-attributes from a string</i>, using the processing instruction

information item's [content] property as the string.</p><p><termdef>A potential xml-model processing

instruction is said to be an <term>xml-model processing

instruction</term> if the <i>parsing result</i> is

not an error when invoking the <i>rules for parsing pseudo-attributes from a string</i>, using

the processing instruction information item's [content] property as

the string.</termdef></p><p>Documents shall not use processing instruction

information items with the [target] property <code>xml-model</code> if they are not xml-model processing

instructions.</p><p>An xml-model processor shall process all xml-model processing instructions properly and shall pass on to the application the full <i>parsing

result</i> for each xml-model processing

instruction.</p><p>An xml-model processing instruction will match the following production:</p><prodlist><prod><grp>XmlModelPI</grp><grp>"&lt;?xml-model" (<nt>S</nt> <nt>PseudoAtts</nt>)?

- (<nt>Char</nt>* "?&gt;" <nt>Char</nt>*) "?&gt;"</grp></prod></prodlist><p>Documents may specify the following <i>pseudo-attributes</i> on xml-model processing instructions, unless otherwise stated:</p><constraint><title><code>href</code></title><p>Specifies the location of the referenced schema. Documents shall specify this <i>pseudo-attribute</i>. Documents shall set the <i>value</i> to a string that matches

the grammar for &lt;IRI-reference&gt; given in RFC 3987 <xref to="rfc3987"/>.</p></constraint><constraint><title><code>type</code></title><p>Specifies the content type of the referenced schema. If unspecified,

the xml-model processor should return a <i>parsing result</i> that would be identical to that when the <i>value</i> is given as <code>application/xml</code>. The <i>value</i> of

this <i>pseudo-attribute</i> is advisory in that it is intended to

be used by an application only when no other source of media type

information becomes available during retrieval of the stylesheet itself.</p></constraint><constraint><title><code>schematypens</code></title><p>Specifies the namespace name of the schema language in which the

referenced schema is written. The application can use this value when determining whether it can make use of the

referenced schema.</p></constraint><constraint><title><code>charset</code></title><p>Specifies the character encoding for the referenced schema. If

specified, documents shall set the <i>value</i> to a valid character

encoding name, which shall be the name or alias

labeled as "preferred MIME name" in the IANA Character Sets registry,

if there is one, or the encoding's name, if none of the aliases are

so labeled <xref to="ianacharset"/>.</p></constraint><constraint><title><code>title</code></title><p>Gives the title (or other human readable description) of the referenced

schema. If specified, documents may use any string

as the <i>value</i>.</p></constraint><constraint><title><code>group</code></title><p>If, for any xml-model processing instruction, its <code>group</code> <i>pseudo-attribute</i> has a non-empty <i>value</i>, special rules for associating schemas apply as follows:</p><ol><li><p>By default only schemas which do not have a <code>group</code> <i>pseudo-attribute</i> specified or schemas which have an empty value in the <code>group</code> <i>pseudo-attribute</i> on the corresponding xml-model processing

instruction are treated as being associated with XML document.</p></li><li><p>An application may

provide an interface for specifying a group name. If the group name

is specified, only schemas which have the same value specified in

the <code>group</code> <i>pseudo-attribute</i> on the corresponding xml-model processing

instruction are considered to be associated with the XML

document.</p></li></ol></constraint><constraint><title><code>phase</code></title><p>Gives the phase name of the validation function for use with a

Schematron schema. If specified, documents may use

any string as the <i>value</i>. If specified, the xml-model

processor should include this information

in the <i>parsing result</i> (regardless of the language of the associated schema).</p><p>If the associated schema is a Schematron schema, and the <i>parsing result</i> includes

the <code>phase</code> <i>pseudo-attribute</i>, then the application is

expected to use the <i>value</i> of this <i>pseudo-attribute</i> as the phase name of the validation function (see ISO/IEC 19757-3,

Section 6.1 <xref to="iso-iec_19757-3_6.1"/>).</p></constraint><p>To allow for extensibility, documents may specify

other <i>pseudo-attributes</i> on xml-model processing instructions.</p><p>This specification provides a way to associate multiple schemas

with a given XML document. Furthermore, there exist other ways certain

schemas can be associated with a given XML document. Regardless of

the association method, this specification does not prescribe the

processing order when multiple schemas are associated with a given

XML document.</p><p>In particular, this specification does not define the interaction

of xml-model processing instructions with <code>xsi:schemaLocation</code> and <code>xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation</code> attributes which provide hints for locating schema in W3C XML Schema.

Applications supporting both xml-model

processing instructions and <code>xsi:schemaLocation/xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation</code> attributes may provide means for specifying which

information takes precedence.</p></clause><annex normative="false"><title>Examples</title><example><p><i>Multiple schemas associated</i></p><pre>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"?&gt;
&lt;book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
 …
&lt;/book&gt;</pre></example><example><p><i>Alternative schema groups</i></p><pre>&lt;?xml-model href="xhtml-transitional.xsd"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="xhtml-strict.xsd" 
   group="Strict"
   title="Check against strict document type"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="xhtml-strict-additional-constraints.sch" 
   group="Strict"
   title="Check against strict document type complex constraints"?&gt;</pre></example></annex><annex normative="false"><title>Suggested use of <code>schematypens</code> for determining schema

language</title><p>Use of a combination of schematypens and type allows for the identification

of many widely used schema languages as shown in the following table.</p><table border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="1"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schema language</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">type</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">schematypens</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>application/xml-dtd</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W3C XML Schema</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified or <code>application/xml</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema</code></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RELAX NG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified or <code>application/xml</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0</code></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RELAX NG – compact syntax</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>application/relax-ng-compact-syntax</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schematron</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified or <code>application/xml</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron</code></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NVDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unspecified or <code>application/xml</code></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><code>http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0</code></td></tr></tbody></table><example><p><i>Multiple schemas associated</i></p><pre>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd" schematypens="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"?&gt;
&lt;book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
 …
&lt;/book&gt;
</pre></example></annex></document>